In this video I'd like to keep working through our example to show how
इस वीडियो में मैं उन्ही हमारे उदाहरणों पर काम करूँगा दिखाने के लिए कैसे
a Neural Network can compute complex non linear hypothesis.
एक न्यूरल नेटवर्क कम्प्यूट कर सकता हैं एक जटिल नॉन-लिनीअर हायपॉथिसस.
In the last video we saw how a Neural Network can be used to
पिछले वीडियो में हमने देखा कैसे एक न्यूरल नेटवर्क इस्तेमाल किया जा सकता है
compute the functions x1 AND x2, and the function x1 OR
कम्प्यूट करने के लिए फ़ंक्शंज़ x1 AND x2, और फ़ंक्शन x1 OR
x2 when x1 and x2 are binary, that is when they take on values 0,1.
x2 जब x1 और x2 हैं बाइनरी, मतलब कि जब वे लेते हैं वैल्यूज़ 0, 1.
We can also have a network to compute negation,
हम बना सकते हैं एक नेटवर्क कम्प्यूट करने के लिए निगेशन,
that is to compute the function not x1.
मतलब कि कम्प्यूट करने के लिए फ़ंक्शन NOT x1.
Let me just write down the ways associated with this network.
मैं सिर्फ़ लिखता हूँ वेट्स इस नेटवर्क में.
We have only one input feature x1 in this case and the bias unit +1.
हमारे पास है केवल एक इनपुट फ़ीचर x1 इस केस में और यह बाइयस यूनिट +1.
And if I associate this with the weights plus 10 and -20,
और यदि मैं जोड़ता हूँ इसे वेट्स प्लस 10 और -20 के साथ,
then my hypothesis is computing this h(x) equals sigmoid (10- 20 x1).
तो मेरी हायपॉथिसस कम्प्यूट करती है यह h(x) बराबर सिग्मोईड(10 - 20 x1).
So when x1 is equal to 0, my hypothesis would
तो जब x1 है 0, मेरी हायपॉथिसस
be computing g(10- 20 x 0) is just 10.
कम्प्यूट करेगी g(10 - 20 x0) जो है सिर्फ़ 10.
And so that's approximately 1, and when x is equal to 1,
और वह है अलगभग 1, और जब x1 है बराबर 1,
this will be g(-10) which is approximately equal to 0.
यह होगा g(1=-10) जो है लगभग बराबर 0 के.
And if you look at what these values are, that's essentially the not x1 function.
और यदि आप देखते हैं कि क्या ये वैल्यूज़ हैं, वह है अनिवार्यत: NOT x1 फ़ंक्शन.
Cells include negations, the general idea is to put
जो करता है निगेशन, सामान्य विचार है कि रखें
that large negative weight in front of the variable you want to negate.
बड़े नेगेटिव वेट सामने वेरीयबल के जो आप निगेट करना चाहते हैं.
Minus 20 multiplied by x1 and
माइनस 20 गुणा x1 से और
that's the general idea of how you end up negating x1.
वह है आम विचार कि कैसे आप कर पाते हैं निगेट x1 को.
And so in an example that I hope that you can figure out yourself.
और इसलिए एक उदाहरण में मैं आशा करता हूँ आप ख़ुद कर पाएँगे.
If you want to compute a function like this NOT x1 AND NOT x2,
यदि आप कम्प्यूट करना चाहते हैं एक फ़ंक्शन इस तरह का x1 AND NOT x2,
part of that will probably be putting large negative weights in front of x1 and
हिस्सा उसका होगा शायद रखना बड़े नेगेटिव वेट्स सामने x1 के और
x2, but it should be feasible.
x2 के, लेकिन यह सम्भव होना चाहिए.
So you get a neural network with just one output unit to compute this as well.
तो आपको मिलता है एक न्यूरल नेटवर्क केवल एक आउट्पुट यूनिट का कम्प्यूट करने के लिए इसे भी.
All right, so this logical function, NOT x1 AND
ठीक है, तो यह लॉजिकल फ़ंक्शन, x1 AND
NOT x2, is going to be equal to 1 if and only if
NOT x2, होगा बराबर 1 के तभी और केवल तभी यदि
x1 equals x2 equals 0.
x1 बराबर है x2 के बराबर है 0.
All right since this is a logical function, this says NOT x1 means x1 must
ठीक है, क्योंकि यह है एक लॉजिकल फ़ंक्शन,यह बताता है NOT x1 का मतलब है x1 होना चाहिए
be 0 and NOT x2, that means x2 must be equal to 0 as well.
0 और NOT x2, उसका मतलब है x2 भी होना चाहिए 0.
So this logical function is equal to 1 if and only if both x1 and
तो यह लॉजिकल फ़ंक्शन होगा 1 केवल तभी जब दोनो x1 और
x2 are equal to 0 and hopefully you should be able to figure out how to
x2 हैं बराबर 0 के और उम्मीद है आप समझ पाएँगे कि कैसे
make a small neural network to compute this logical function as well.
बनाना है एक छोटा न्यूरल नेटवर्क कम्प्यूट करने के लिए इस लॉजिकल फ़ंक्शन को भी.
Now, taking the three pieces that we have put together as the network for
अब, लेते हुए तीनो हिस्से जो हमने साथ रखे नेटवर्क की तरह
computing x1 AND x2, and the network computing for computing NOT x1 AND NOT x2.
कम्प्यूट करने के लिए x1 AND x2, और नेटवर्क कम्प्यूट करने के लिए NOT x1 AND NOT x2.
And one last network computing for computing x1 OR x2, we should be able
और एक आख़िरी नेटवर्क कम्प्यूट करने के लिए x1 OR x2, हमें कर पाना चाहिए
to put these three pieces together to compute this x1 XNOR x2 function.
इन तीन हिस्सों को एक साथ कम्प्यूट करने के लिए यह x1 XNOR x2 फ़ंक्शन.
And just to remind you if this is x1, x2,
और सिर्फ याद दिलाने के लिए अगर यह है, x1, x2,
this function that we want to compute would have negative examples here and
यह फ़ंक्शन जो हम चाहते हैं कम्प्यूट करना उसमें होंगे नेगेटिव इग्ज़ाम्पल्ज़ यहाँ और
here, and we'd have positive examples there and there.
यहाँ, और हमारे पास हैं पॉज़िटिव इग्ज़ाम्पल्ज़ वहाँ और वहाँ.
And so clearly this will need a non linear decision boundary
और तो स्पष्ट रूप से इसे चाहिए एक नॉन-लिनीअर डिसीज़न सीमा रेखा
in order to separate the positive and negative examples.
अलग करने के लिए पॉज़िटिव और नेगेटिव इग्ज़ाम्पल को.
Let's draw the network.
चलो बनाते हैं नेटवर्क.
I'm going to take my input +1, x1, x2 and create my first hidden unit here.
मैं लूँगा मेरी इनपुट +1, x1, x2 और बनाऊँगा मेरी पहली हिडन यूनिट यहाँ.
I'm gonna call this a 21 cuz that's my first hidden unit.
मैं कहूँगा उसे a21 क्योंकि वह है मेरी पहली हिडन यूनिट.
And I'm gonna copy the weight over from the red network, the x1 and x2.
और मैं कॉपी करूँगा वेट वहाँ लाल नेटवर्क से, x1 AND x2.
As well so then -30, 20, 20.
भी ठीक है तब -30, 20, 20.
Next let me create a second hidden unit which I'm going to call a 2 2.
इसके बाद मैं बनाता हूँ दूसरी हिडन यूनिट जिसे मैं कहूँगा a22.
That is the second hidden unit of layer two.
वह है दूसरी हिडन यूनिट लेयर दो की.
I'm going to copy over the cyan that's work in the middle, so
मैं कॉपी करूँगा सायऐन नेटवर्क यहाँ मध्य में, तो
I'm gonna have the weights 10 -20 -20.
मेरे पास वेट्स होंगे 10, -20, -20.
And so, let's pull some of the truth table values.
और इसलिए, चलो लेते हैं कुछ ट्रूथ टेबल वैल्यूज़.
For the red network, we know that was computing the x1 and
लाल नेटवर्क के लिए, हम जानते हैं वह कम्प्यूट कर रहा था x1 AND
x2, and so this will be approximately 0 0 0 1,
x2, और इसलिए यह होगा लगभग 0 0 0 1,
depending on the values of x1 and x2, and for a 2 2, the cyan network.
निर्भर करते हुए x1 और x2 की वैल्यूज़ पर, और a22 के लिए सायऐन नेटवर्क.
What do we know?
हम क्या जानते हैं?
The function NOT x1 AND NOT x2, that outputs 1 0 0 0, for
फ़ंक्शन NOT x1 AND NOT x2, वह आउट्पुट करता है 1 0 0 0,
the 4 values of x1 and x2.
चार वैल्यूज़ के लिए x1 और x2 की.
Finally, I'm going to create my output node, my output unit that is a 3 1.
अंत में मैं बनाऊँगा मेरा आउट्पुट नोड, मेरी आउट्पुट यूनिट जो है a31.
This is one more output h(x) and I'm going to copy over the old network for that.
यह है एक और आउट्पुट h(x) और मैं करूँगा कॉपी पुराना नेटवर्क उसके लिए.
And I'm going to need a +1 bias unit here, so you draw that in, And
और मुझे चाहिए एक a +1 बाइयस यूनिट यहाँ, आप आप बनाते हैं उसे, और
I'm going to copy over the weights from the green networks.
मैं कॉपी करूँगा वेट हरे नेटवर्क से.
So that's -10, 20, 20 and we know earlier that this computes the OR function.
तो वह हैं -10, 20, 20 और हम पहले से जानते हैं कि यह कम्प्यूट करता है OR फ़ंक्शन.
So let's fill in the truth table entries.
तो चलो भर लेते हैं ट्रूथ टेबल एंट्रीज़.
So the first entry is 0 OR 1 which can be 1 that makes 0 OR
तो पहली एंट्री है 0 OR 1 जो हो सकता है 1 जो बनाता है 0 OR
0 which is 0, 0 OR 0 which is 0, 1 OR 0 and that falls to 1.
0 जो है 0, 0 OR 0 जो है 0, 1 OR 0 और वह बनाता है 1.
And thus h(x) is equal to 1 when either both x1 and x2 are zero or
और इसलिए h(x) है बराबर 1 जब या दोनो x1 और x2 ज़ीरो हैं या
when x1 and x2 are both 1 and concretely h(x) outputs 1
जब दोनो x1 और x2 1 हैं और वास्तव में h(x) आउट्पुट करता है 1
exactly at these two locations and then outputs 0 otherwise.
बिल्कुल इन दो स्थानो पर और फिर आउट्पुट करता है 0 अन्यथा.
And thus will this neural network, which has a input layer,
और ऐसा ही यह न्यूरल नेटवर्क करेगा, जिसमें है एक इनपुट लेयर,
one hidden layer, and one output layer,
एक हिडन लेयर, और एक आउट्पुट लेयर,
we end up with a nonlinear decision boundary that computes this XNOR function.
हमें मिलती है एक नॉन-लिनीअर निर्णायक सीमा रेखा जो कम्प्यूट करती है यह XNOR फ़ंक्शन.
And the more general intuition is that in the input layer,
और अधिक सामान्य अनुभव है कि इनपुट लेयर में,
we just have our four inputs.
हमारे पास सिर्फ़ हैं चार इन्पुट्स.
Then we have a hidden layer,
फिर हमारे पास है एक हिडन लेयर,
which computed some slightly more complex functions of the inputs that its shown
जिसने कम्प्यूट थोड़ा अधिक जटिल फ़ंक्शन इन्पुट्स का जो दिखाया है
here this is slightly more complex functions.
यहाँ यह है थोड़ा अधिक पेचीदा फ़ंक्शन्स
And then by adding yet
और फिर जोड़ने से और
another layer we end up with an even more complex non linear function.
एक अन्य लेयर हमें मिलता है एक और भी जटिल नॉन-लिनीअर फ़ंक्शन.
And this is a sort of intuition about why neural networks can compute
और यह है एक तरह से अनुभव कि क्यों न्यूरल नेटवर्क्स कम्प्यूट कर सकते हैं
pretty complicated functions.
बहुत जटिल फ़ंक्शन्स.
That when you have multiple layers you have relatively simple function of
वह जब आपके पास हैं कई लेयर्स आपके पास हैं अपेक्षाकृत सरल फ़ंक्शन
the inputs of the second layer.
दूसरी लेयर की इन्पुट्स के.
But the third layer I can build on that to complete even more complex functions, and
लेकिन तीसरी लेयर बना सकती है उस पर पूरा करने के लिए और भी अधिक जटिल फ़ंक्शन्स, और
then the layer after that can compute even more complex functions.
फिर उसके बाद की लेयर कम्प्यूट कर सकती है और भी अधिक जटिल फ़ंक्शन्स.
To wrap up this video,
समाप्त करने के लिए इस वीडियो को,
I want to show you a fun example of an application of a the Neural Network
मैं आपको दिखाना चाहता हूँ एक मज़ेदार उदाहरण एक ऐप्लिकेशन का न्यूरल नेटवर्क की
that captures this intuition of the deeper layers computing more complex features.
जो ले सकती है यह अनुभव गहरी लेयर्स का कम्प्यूट करते हुए अधिक जटिल फ़ीचर्ज़.
I want to show you a video of that customer a good friend of mine
मैं आपको दिखाना चाहता हूँ एक वीडियो उस ग्राहक का मेरा अच्छा मित्र है
Yann LeCunj.
यान्न लेकुंज.
Yann is a professor at New York University, NYU and
यान्न एक प्रोफ़ेसर है न्यू यॉर्क यूनिवर्सिटी, एनवाययू में, और
he was one of the early pioneers of Neural Network reasearch and
वे थे न्यूरल नेटवर्क में अनुसंधान के अगुआ लोगों में से एक और
is sort of a legend in the field now and his ideas are used in
हैं एक तरह से प्रसिद्ध इस क्षेत्र में अब और उनके विचार इस्तेमाल किए जाते हैं
all sorts of products and applications throughout the world now.
हर तरह के प्रॉडक्ट्स और ऐप्लिकेशन्स में पूरे विश्व में अब.
So I wanna show you a video from some of his early work in which he was using
तो मैं आपको दिखाना चाहता हूँ एक वीडियो उनके कुछ शुरू के काम का जिसमें वे इस्तेमाल कर रहे थे
a neural network to recognize handwriting, to do handwritten digit recognition.
एक न्यूरल नेटवर्क पहचानने के लिए लिखावट, करने के हस्तलिखित अंको की पहचान.
You might remember early in this class, at the start of this class I said that
आपको शायद याद हो शुरू में इस क्लास में, शुरुआत में इस क्लास में मैंने कहा था कि
one of the earliest successes of neural networks was trying to use it to read zip
शूरु की न्यूरल नेटवर्क की सफलताओं में से एक था इस्तेमाल करना इसे पढ़ने के लिए ज़िप
codes to help USPS Laws and read postal codes.
कोड्स मदद करने के लिए यूएसपीएस लॉज़ / क़ानून और पढ़ने के लिए पोस्टल कोड्स.
So this is one of the attempts,
तो यह है उनमें से एक प्रयास,
this is one of the algorithms used to try to address that problem.
यह है उन अल्गोरिद्म्स में से एक इस्तेमाल किया गया सम्बोधित करने के लिए उस प्रॉब्लम को.
In the video that I'll show you this area here
वीडियो में जो मैं दिखाऊँगा आपको यह क्षेत्र यहाँ
is the input area that shows a canvasing character shown to the network.
है इनपुट एरिया जो दिखता हैं कॉरेस्पॉंडिंग अंक दिखाया गया नेटवर्क को.
This column here shows a visualization of the features computed by sort of the first
यह कॉलम यहाँ दिखाता है एक विज़ूअलाइज़ेशन फ़ीचर्ज़ का कम्प्यूट किए गए पहली
hidden layer of the network.
हिडन लेयर से नेटवर्क की.
So that the first hidden layer of the network and so the first hidden layer,
तो वह है पहली हिडन लेयर नेटवर्क की और इसलिए पहली हिडन लेयर,
this visualization shows different features.
यह विज़ूअलाइज़ेशन दिखाता है विभिन्न फ़ीचर्ज़.
Different edges and lines and so on detected.
अलग किनारे और लाइने और इसी तरह कुछ कुछ चीज़ें पता चलीं.
This is a visualization of the next hidden layer.
यह है विज़ूअलाइज़ेशन अगली हिडन लेयर की.
It's kinda harder to see, harder to understand the deeper, hidden layers, and
यह एक तरह से थोड़ा कठिन है देखना, कठिन है समझना गहरी, हिडन लेयर्स, और
that's a visualization of why the next hidden layer is confusing.
वह है एक विज़ूअलाइज़ेशन कि क्यों अगली हिडन लेयर अस्पष्ट है.
You probably have a hard time seeing what's going
आपको शायद कठिन लगे देख पाना क्या हो रहा है
on much beyond the first hidden layer, but
पहली हिडन लेयर के आगे, लेकिन
then finally, all of these learned features get fed to the upper layer.
फिर अंत में, सारे ये लर्न किए हुए फ़ीचर्ज़ फ़ीड किए जाते हैं ऊपरी लेयर को.
And shown over here is the final answer, it's the final predictive value for
और यहाँ दिखाया गया है अंतिम उत्तर, यह अंतिम प्रिडिक्टेड वैल्यू
what handwritten digit the neural network thinks it is being shown.
क्या हस्तलिखित अंक के लिए न्यूरल नेटवर्क सोचता है यह दिखाया जा रहा है.
So let's take a look at the video.
तो चलो देखते हैं वीडियो.
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
So I hope you enjoyed the video and that this hopefully gave you some intuition
तो मैं उम्मीद करता हूँ आपको मज़ा आया होगा वीडियो में और कि यह शायद देगा आपको कुछ अनुभव
about the source of pretty complicated functions neural networks can learn.
कि काफ़ी जटिल फ़ंक्शंज़ के उदगम का जो न्यूरल नेटवर्क लर्न कर सकता है.
In which it takes its input this image, just takes this input, the raw pixels and
जिसमें यह लेता है इसकी इनपुट यह इमिज, सिर्फ़ लेता है यह इनपुट, रॉ पिक्सेल्स और
the first hidden layer computes some set of features.
पहली हिडन लेयर कम्प्यूट करती है कुछ सेट फ़ीचर्ज़ का.
The next hidden layer computes even more complex features and
अगली हिडन लेयर कम्प्यूट करती है थोड़े और जटिल फ़ीचर्ज़ और
even more complex features.
और भी अधिक जटिल फ़ीचर्ज़.
And these features can then be used by essentially the final
और ये फ़ीचर्ज़ तब किए जा सकते हैं आवश्यक रूप से अंतिम
layer of the logistic classifiers to make accurate predictions
लेयर में लॉजिस्टिक क्लैसिफ़ायअर की करने के लिए एकदम सही प्रिडिक्शन्स
without the numbers that the network sees.
नम्बर्ज़ के बारे में जो नेटवर्क देखता है.